Hips are one type of three trait structure and are used when implementing a priority queue, a priority
queue is one type of data structure that we have seen in the queues, and we have said that we are going
to learn about the priority queue when we are going to talk about the hips in prior to queue.
Data can be added in any order.
Conversely, when extracting data, the smallest value are chosen first.
Being able to freely add data and then extract the smallest value first define a priority queue.
Moving on.
Let's look at the heap heaps data structure.
As a rule of keeps, a child number is always greater than its burden.
No.
Let's try adding a number to that heap.
We put it you put it here, because the number that is first placed on to the end of the line is the
parent.
No happens to be greater that child and parent swear.
So we need to make the children is greater than that per.
This operation repeats until no additional swab occurs.
The permanent one is less than the child, five.
So since the parent is smaller, no swap occurs.
The addition of the number to the heap is now complete when extracting a number from a heap.
The number of that on the top is removed.
So when we extract it, it will be removed.
No, who will take that permanent position from this heap in a heap?
The smallest value is held in the top position.
So because the top number has removed, the heap structure needs to be reorganized.
So we go and we get the number at the end of the line moves to the top, which is six.
And when one of the child numbers is less than the parent, the smallest and the lowest of the adjacent
child numbers swept with the parent.
So year three, you will be swept.
So the parent six was greater than the child to the right five, which was in turn greater than the
child that left three.
So that left the child and the parent swept.
This operation repeats until no additional swap occurs.
Six is greater than four, but less than eight, so it was swept for with a six.
And we go to the right side.
Five is less than seven, so no need to make any changes.
Now the permanent three is less than the four to the left and five to the right.
The extraction of a number from the hip is now complete.
In this way, heaps can be used to quickly extract the smallest data.
However.
Extraction of data in the middle of the three cannot be performed, hips are used in things like priority
queues and Dijkstra algorithm.
We will see that Dijkstra algorithm in the next few days.
So this is about the hips.
Now let's move to implement it into C language and learn and solve the exercise about implementing hips
in.